Okay, welcome back. Um,
we're going to move away from
pre-training now, and I think we'll get
into uh, in my opinion, some of the
messier parts um, of language modeling.
I mean, data is always pretty messy, but
I think post-training and everything
that goes along with it is really, you
know, kind of artisal in many ways. Um,
so to set the stage, thus far I think
you can kind of get to a souped-up
version of GPT3. Uh, I'm sure you can
use more flops, you can get more data,
so you can make something a little bit
better than GPT3, but ultimately um, the
amount of utility you can get from
something like GPT3, which is a very big
strong base model, is ultimately a
little bit limited, right? Um, when we
went from GPT3 to something like chat
GPT, um, I'm sure if your first exposure
to to these systems was chat GPT, it was
like kind of amazing. If you go back and
interact with GPT3, you'll be like, what
what is this thing? What is the point of
this thing, right? And the only thing
you could really do with it was things
like copywriting or these like sort of
fun little tasks where you didn't really
need reliability or instruction
following. So today we are going to get
from GPT3 to something that is getting
basically close to chat GPT. Right? So
this is the very first part that we
need. Um and in the next lecture we will
go from chat GPT to um GPT01 or you know
any of the thinking models that we have
today. Right? So those are going to be
the two parts and the process that will
take us from the left to the right will
be a process that you know usually
people call post training.
Um, and I want to sort of emphasize just
kind of how remarkable it is that we can
do instruction following. Um,
instruction following is um, this
process of being able to put in a pretty
long complicated prompt and get back,
you know, very reasonable answers. Um,
at the GP3 GPT3 level, fine grain
control of these systems was basically
impossible. Like you would put in a
bunch of fot prompts and you'd say,
well, if my examples were good enough,
I'd get something reasonable. um in
practice your ability to steer these
models are limited. Um but once GPT 3.5
and GPT4 comes around, you start getting
these examples of very long sort of
programmatic prompts and then the model
really oneshotting um the whole prompt.
And so what does it what do you really
need in order to get this kind of
instruction following um to work? And so
pre-training is always important. It's
kind of the basis on which we build all
of this, right? So if we ignore
pre-training and we just try to
post-train our way to victory, we will
get none of the things that we want,
absolutely none of it. So pre-training
is critical because it scales in this
very diverse broad way. Um but once we
have pre-training, we have to then
extract the kinds of behaviors that we
want out of this kind of primordial soup
that is pre-training, right? Um, and to
do that we are going to have to do much
more explicit data collection, much more
explicit steering and a lot of messy
engineering that in some ways we didn't
have to do so far. I mean the
architecture stuff you might think is
messy. I think it really doesn't compare
to the messiness of of real world post
training. Um, and so you know we're
going to go and collect some data or you
know we will talk as if we are going to
go and collect some data. Um, we're
going to talk about what that data looks
like. um how to train with it um and
what the scale of that looks like.
Um and I will preface the rest of this
lecture and say, you know, information
about frontier post training is honestly
pretty sparse in many many ways. If you
look at the the uh materials that I'm
going to reference today, um a lot of
it's going to be actually pretty old.
It's going to be before the competition
from chat GPT started to heat up. Um so
for example the RHF paper um learning to
summarize from human feedback you know
that that's actually incredibly
detailed. I'll point to that today in
lecture you know if you're interested I
suggest you go read some of the
appendices you know it contains things
like detailed annotation guidelines how
they were instructing people to to you
know give feedback to the models.
Similarly with anthropics hh paper back
in uh 2022. Um and then you know now
that competition has heated up basically
none of the vendors want to release any
information about their post-training
processes right the data is very much a
trade secret um and so we are not going
to be able to talk about annotation
guidelines and things like that for
anything that resembles a modern
language model um in you know we do have
closed source oh sorry open source
models um but on the other hand a lot of
the open- source uh recipes rely on
distillation I think its nature is very
different from what the uh frontier labs
are doing in terms of like human data
collection which is really a very tricky
and messy thing and and I'll try to
point out some of that but it'll be
difficult to talk about some of that uh
very comprehensively
um okay and then uh you know just as a
example of this you know I was doing
some pre-ressearch for this lecture um
earlier um and I found this very fun
example back in 2023 about you know the
trade secretness of post- training data
um where I guess you know scale AI's
internal documents got leaked at some
point and they had a whole bunch of very
frank conversations about what was
happening in post- trainining data land
and one of them was like well they were
trying to make Google barred better but
they couldn't figure out why you know
GPT4 was so much better and so they said
well let's like we need to like reverse
engineer what's happening and we need to
get our uh annotators to produce
responses that are more detailed uh or
and better than GPT4 right so these
kinds of like competitive dynamics are
happening all the time and that's also
why some of this detail is going to be
missing from today's lecture. Um that
said, algorithm wise, we do have a
pretty good handle on what is happening,
right? But algorithms are not really the
the secret sauce. It's not where a lot
of the leverage is. It's going to be the
data. Um so if we look at um the sort of
RLHF papers, we see a very
straightforward recipe, right? Two-part
recipe. The first part is you go and
collect some demonstration data, right?
So for every sort of prompt, you want
some annotator to provide supervised
fine-tuning data. So you know, reference
responses for that prompt, right? And
you're going to do some fine-tune. Then
after you have that, you're going to do
some reinforcement learning of some kind
to try to shape the behavior of the
model to be sort of more aligned or more
in line with what sort of humans think
are good responses. Right? So I'm going
to start by talking about this very
first phase, which is the SFT part of um
post- training. Um, and this is the part
that's really basically all about data,
right? We all know how to SFT a model
that's basically exactly the same as
pre-training. So, the only real
difference with some minor variation is
going to be the training data. So, I
will focus on the training data almost
entirely for this part um of the
lecture. Okay. Um, with a little bit of
discussion about the method right after.
Okay. So, we will go through the data.
We're going to, you know, look at some
examples. I'll talk about some
historical developments and what kind of
the trends are at least in open- source
post-training data land. Um, and then I
will talk about some pitfalls, some ways
in which collecting this kind of data is
much harder uh than you think. And you
know, if you've taken classes like 224N,
um, you're going to sort of find some
things that are very reminiscent of, uh,
issues that you see when you start
building, you know, classic supervised
deep learning models from scratch. Um,
so let me take a moment to pause, um,
and then just talk about the progression
of SFT data over the years. Um, I think
I'm going to go, you know, top left to
bottom right. That's roughly my
chronological ordering. And there's been
a lot of different tricks and a lot of
things that people have done in the
open- source language modeling land to
try to you know both improve system
performance and to to try to understand
what factors uh of this kind of data are
useful to uh train models. I think
really the oldest and you know in some
ways the most visionary of this is
things like Fla. Um this was used to
train the T5 model by Google. um their
rough idea for this was to say well NLP
people have already collected a bunch of
supervised data sets of like inputs and
outputs we should just train the model
on all of these right reasonable uh
thing to try um turned out for various
reasons this was not the right thing to
do I'll talk about that later um
self-instruct and other sort of
follow-ups to that um this was also sort
of very forward-looking um in terms of
its thinking was saying well why can't
we use the model itself to generate data
well models are getting better all the
time. Um, and in fact, they might even
be better than some of our annotators.
Why don't we get models to, you know,
write very um very good highquality
responses to our inputs? And that's sort
of the self-instruct idea. And then
there came a bunch of sort of
distillation style approaches. Um,
Alpaca is one of them. Um, the Berkeley
folks had one called Vikunia in which
they were using um sort of online user
shared prompts as sort of the way to to
as the inputs to distill on. Um, and
then there were sort of other efforts
that were more entirely human-driven
like open assistant. You can think of
this like kind of like Wikipedia. It was
a bunch of people getting together to
write prompts and responses. Um, and
then you have sort of a a new generation
wizard LM and Tulu 3 and others of
saying, well, we know that language
models are very good synthetic data
generators. Why don't we come up with
increasingly complicated ways of
generating uh instruction following data
using language models? And then finally,
I I'll touch briefly on this. Um, SFTP
and sort of post- training has changed
yet again in recent years because I
think the focus is less on chat and much
more on agents and tool use. And so
there's a now a new generation of sort
of SFT pipelines that are designed to
generate sort of tool use and agentic
data. Right? So this is roughly you know
a bunch of different developments in uh
post- training data land at least in the
open source world. So in the closed
source world where you know well some of
the companies may be distilling each
other but where you're also collecting
human data you know how you're
collecting the human data is a big
important ingredient that's not
reflected in any of this discussion.
Okay I can pause here in case anyone has
uh questions um before I move on to well
what we're going to do next is look at
some of the details of these data sets.
>> Good. Oh yeah. So basically for post
training we need the input output output
pairs right
>> that's right input output pairs like
>> does the correctness of those input
output matters like how hard does it
>> yes so the question was how much does
the correctness of the input output
pairs matter um that's a nuanced
question I mean I think the the top
level answer is you should go collect
the highest quality responses you can
because the bad stuff will teach the
model to do bad stuff on the other hand
it turns out that you can SFT models on
all sorts of strange things and they
will learn to follow instructions. Um I
think Percy's former student had a paper
in which you're like training uh models
without even the the responses or
something and you can train models to
like you know be instruction following.
And so there's a lot of like
pre-training generalization behaviors
that let you get away with worse quality
data. So it's a it's actually a pretty
nuanced question um what you need in uh
instruction following data.
Okay, good.
So um I want to maybe start with fawn.
Um you know I think fawn is very much
like a forwardlooking
uh data set for its time right like it
sort of established this idea of doing
this like multitask post training. Just
if you're going to do downstream tasks
go collect all the downstream tasks and
train on it. Very reasonable but smart
idea at the time. Um but if we look at
what's in fla we actually find that you
know it's a little bit of a strange data
set. um you know you have this thing
that's like well here's an email and
then there's this like thing that gets
appended which is like write a subject
line for this email and then the subject
line goes on the right um this is a very
strange thing like I don't think you've
ever probably prompted you know a model
to do a task like this let alone the
instructions at the very end right and
the reason why you get something like
this is because fla is generated from
existing data sets right so there's a
data set called enron emails this is
basically a way to turn enron emails
into a supervised task, right? Because
it has a body and a subject. You can
make this subject a prediction task. Um,
you know, similarly, you know, you have
summarization task. This is, um, I don't
know if this was taken from CNN Daily
Mail or Exxon, but it was taken from one
of the big major summarization data
sets, right? Write highlights for this
article. Take the article part of a
summarization data set, put the summ
summary on the right. But you
immediately notice, you know, compared
to something like ChatgPT, the summaries
are very short. Um in fact if you look
really closely the summaries are often
hallucinated like there's a bunch of
details that are not in the inputs. Um
and in some ways you know related to
this question right the original NLP
data sets from which font was built was
not the highest of quality right and so
when you train on this thing you also
inherit a whole bunch of sort of
deficiencies from those data sets and
the unnaturalness of the structure of
these data sets also sort of carry down
all the way. Um and so this is a very
smart idea. Font is a very smart idea to
create this big data set out of um of
these uh data set existing benchmarks.
But really the unnaturalenness really
gets you. Oh and I'll I'll mention one
more thing going back one slide. I think
when Flawn was originally constructed
sort of part of the theory of how
post-training should work was that you
needed scale, right? Like in
pre-training we know we need a lot of
scale. So you might also think that in
post training we need a ton of scale to
unlock capabilities. Um and so because
of that they took tons of data sets and
lots of data and had this gigantic data
set. We'll see sort of later on that a
lot of these data sets just get really
much smaller and it still works. And so
really part of the change from fawn to
later data sets is this observation that
if you have a sufficiently strong big
pre-trained model, you can actually get
away with very few highquality examples
because of pre-training generalization
is going to get you quite a bit of the
way. And so it's kind of the wrong point
in some ways on the quality uh quantity
trade-off although you know there was no
way to know until we sort of explored
the full space of these data sets. Um
and then I think you know after that the
the maybe next point in how sort of
instruction tuning data sets our
understanding of it changed um was after
chat GPD came out um some of my students
um you know did this thing called alpaca
where they distilled chat GPT traces to
get input output pairs right um so this
is an example from that data set you get
you know more naturalook inputs um
longer sort of chatty outputs because of
course it's it's taken from chat GPT Um
and what we found um was that these
kinds of examples now reliably induced
kind of um chatgpt like behavior on
models. uh importantly you know only
when we did it to the original uh llama
models um so pre-training post-training
you know both of them need to work out
right but we did find you know that this
was was kind of the point at which these
things started to work and so I think
people realized at this point that if
you got this kind of sort of chat style
data it was actually not that hard to
build chatgpt style systems you know
getting the details right is still hard
but you know to get most of the way so
then I think there was this big push to
create essentially the highest quality
human-driven version of this these kinds
of data sets. Um to give you a little
bit more context at the time I think
after chat GPD came out and alpaca came
out I think there was this enormous
optimism that if only we could uh
collect a sufficiently high quality and
large you know instruction tuning data
set we could then sort of catch up and
match a lot of the performance of these
big closed source labs. there's a lot of
sort of energy and excitement uh to
building these data sets. And so in that
context, open assistant is this big
crowdsourced effort to build such a data
set, right? So a lot of volunteers got
together and they said, well, we're
going to, you know, come up with really
hard and interesting prompts. We're
going to come up with good highquality
responses and we're going to do it at
scale in the same way that Wikipedia,
you know, managed to produce something
very high quality at scale. Um, a very
admirable, very impressive effort um
that generated actually a decent amount
of data. I forget if it's like 10,000 or
or more examples um before sort of
stalling out as a as a as a as a
project. I can I can maybe you know talk
about that if someone's interested. Um
but if you look now we have you know
chat style inputs very long detailed
sort of high quality expert responses on
the right. Good stuff. Um I'll talk
about some of the pitfalls later as
well. Okay. Finally I've taken this from
some of the newest of the instruction
tuning data sets. we've really started
to move as a field or you know in terms
of the products that people want from
just a chat interface to something
that's like a full agent system right so
we don't want just textual responses we
want tool calls we want you know uh
to-do lists if you've ever used cloud
code or or codeex you you know that like
it produces a to-do list to like check
off as it goes um we want all of those
things right and so SFT data now if you
look at for example Neotron so that's
Nvidia's open source efforts their SF
data uh a big chunk of it is these kinds
of AsiTentic SFT uh examples where not
only do you have the responses which are
provided in the sort of uh assistant
field here um but also tool calls that
can happen in parallel alongside the
text right and this is SFT data so this
is you know explicitly sort of
supervised into the model um and so now
we're sort of moving much more towards
these like structured uh formats
okay and I've been talking about this as
I've gone through but we've seen sort of
big sort of higher level transitions in
how we think about and build these kinds
of data sets. It's useful to roughly
internalize these sort of like
perspectives. Um, one of them is kind of
this chattiness thing. Um, it's hard for
me to like fully articulate what this
is, but there's a sense in which the
classic NLP data sets, even the high
quality ones, were very like input to
like programmatic output almost, right?
Um, but people don't really want to talk
to an NLP benchmark. They want to talk
to people. And so there was this big
shift that has happened towards more
detailed human-like responses. Um
there's a big shift towards higher
quality annotators and much more detail.
Open assistant is a good example of this
of having experts write your responses.
And then finally, you know, tool use and
figuring out the right sort of, you
know, interface and API for all this has
been a big sort of final shift that's
been happening. I'm sure things will
keep changing but these are kind of some
highle you know factors uh to think
about uh in terms of how SFT data has
changed over the last few years.
Okay. Um I'll talk about sort of all
sorts of you know pitfalls or challenges
in a moment. Um any questions on on the
specifics of data sets and things like
this?
Good. Okay. Um so now I think let's say
you are put in charge of collecting
human annotation data for SFT. um what
kinds of sort of things should you be
mindful of right um there's lots of
formatting things right that you might
want to think about there's also things
like knowledge how much knowledge should
be put into the responses how how much
data points do you want and like how do
you deal with kind of uh safety of your
model like what kinds of safety data
should you be collecting
um and I think one thing I want to
highlight is length is and style
variation in general is a very very big
part of this like post-training process.
People say, you know, Claude has a
different tone than chat GPT, you know,
chat GPT is too chatty, so on and so
forth. All of these are, you know,
conscious decisions that are made by the
data collection folks. Um, and also we
see like very wide variation if you look
at the data sets in terms of the length
of the responses. Um and one thing I do
want to kind of highlight is when you go
and evaluate preferences um these
stylistic factors matter a ton right so
people will get very easily tricked not
I don't know if tricked is the right
word you know they will very often
select responses that have bulletointed
lists in their outputs uh or they will
select responses that have you know more
and longer detail I think part of this
is very natural especially if you're in
an evaluation setting where you put in
front of two examples and someone asks
you which one's better. I think you know
more detailed and list-like responses
are generally good. Um but this does
induce very explicit distortions in the
kinds of you know uh tone that a chatbot
has uh relative to people. Um
these factors Oh yeah.
>> So how do complex matters in the data
set?
>> I'll talk about them later.
>> Um and you can ask me questions if I
don't fully answer your question there.
Um so uh right but I think the thing
about style right and the thing to be
careful about is if you're looking at
engagement signals as most of these
companies are um it's very very easy to
fool yourself into thinking you're
getting better data when in reality um
your model's capabilities are not
changing. So if you look at sort of all
of these different kinds of like you
know uh post-training data sets that you
can train on um you'll see big
variations in preferences when you train
on some of these things. So that's kind
of the right column over there alpaca
eval for example but really it doesn't
necessarily change you know standard
benchmarking evaluations. So your models
aren't necessarily smarter because
you've trained on certain kinds of post-
training data at least in these ones. Um
but you can very much shift sort of the
engagement signals. And so this is kind
of telling you you know you want to
think about style control separately
from capabilities control.
Okay. The other thing and this I think
is is a quite in many ways important
sort of thing to think about in terms of
how we collect and think about post-
training data. Um I think open assistant
is very instructive because it was an
effort that was you know intended to be
the highest quality in some ways uh
post-training data. Um, and so you often
see things like this, like for example,
this uh reference, sorry, this response
contains a reference to an article. This
JM Michelle L, the pay of corporate
executives and blah blah blah, right?
Um, and so this is actually teaching the
model kind of two different things at
once. Let's say you you're uh sfting on
this data. So first of all, you know,
you're doing next token prediction. So
it's teaching the model about, you know,
this Bivvens J and Michelle L citation.
Um, it's also telling the model another
thing which is when you're giving a
response, a good thing to do is to give
a reference, right? So these are two
different mechanisms that are sort of
going on at once. You're teaching the
model about different pieces of
knowledge, which is good because you
want the model to be knowledgeable, but
you're also teaching the model to emit
detailed knowledge. Um, and this is
sometimes problematic because what this
is going to force the model to do is
sometimes it will misgeneralize and it
will sort of hallucinate out a reference
instead of actually giving a proper
reference, right? Models don't really
know necessarily whether a reference is
uh true or false. Um, and there's been
sort of a lot of interesting arguments
that people have made around this. Um
and I think the folklore which I think
is not wrong there's some you know good
empirical evidence to support this
folklore is that if you train a model
especially at the SFT phase to uh emit
facts that it does not know um this will
make it hallucinate right because the
model as I said is is trying to
generalize two behaviors at once it's
trying to generalize the knowledge but
also the format and so teaching it
something where you have the format and
a sort of piece of unknown knowledge is
kind of teaching the model to force
forcibly emit unknown knowledge. Um, and
people have shown that if you train on,
for example, um, uh,
information that that you don't really
know, then this leads to sort of
hallucination and sort of overfitting
uh, to pieces of knowledge. Whereas if
you're training on only known facts, you
don't necessarily see this. Um, John
Schulman makes a sort of separate
argument, which is that this is the
reason why you need reinforcement
learning and training. I mean, this is
unsurprising because if you know John
Schulman, he's like a reinforcement
learning guy, right? like he made PO you
know of course he is very
pro-reinforcement learning but the
argument is sound right that in some
ways in order to teach the model what it
knows and doesn't know you do have to be
policy dependent right you can't have an
external person telling like sort of
shoving knowledge down your throat if
you want the model to be sort of
calibrated about what it knows and
doesn't know
okay um and so to put that piece
together right um you might not want to
train on the highest quality data if the
model doesn't already know that data,
right? Tail knowledge can actually
sometimes be actively harmful in that it
might induce hallucinations, especially
if it's associated with markers like
reference colon, right? That that'll
force the model to emit a reference
afterwards. Um, I'll talk about RLHF
later, but you know, this is one of the
reasons why reinforcement learning is
important and useful, right? For things
that are model dependent, like knowing
what you know, RL is a very useful way
to teach models to not say things that
it does not know. Um and so knowledge
storage is actually very messy and a
very nuanced concept. Um you don't
really want to just say ah yes just pack
knowledge in there. You want to be very
careful about exactly what supervision
you're throwing in at the post- training
stage. This is one of the reasons why I
think post- training is quite messy
right. You have to deal with all these
realities of serving a system eventually
to a user. Yes.
>> What's the definition of tail knowledge?
>> Yeah I don't think there's like a formal
definition of tail knowledge. For
example, in the past when I've worked on
things like this, um it's been things
like uh the number of times that uh
sorry, the length uh of a Wikipedia
article for example might be a proxy for
its you know well-knownness and then you
might say ah yes if we train on stuff
that's not wellknown we do see that the
model hallucinates more right but
there's no formal like ah yes this is
tail and this is not knowledge because
knowledge itself can't really be pinned
down precisely
okay yeah
>> borrow is going to help to not
hallucinate on me like what is it like
intuitive right
>> the question was what why would RL help
for hallucinations um and the reason why
RL might help um let me give kind of
like a folk story for why this might
help imagine um the model has internal
to it like a I know something direction
inside its activations right at SFT time
maybe what's happening is you forced it
to you know generate references from
your SF data and so you know it's just
going to generate references no matter
what but When you RL, you might notice
that you get good rewards when you
generate references in the I know stuff
direction and you get bad, you know,
rewards when you generate references in
the I don't know direction. And so then
you might then learn to generalize that
like I know things or don't know things
activations into whether you emit a
reference, right? So it's possible that
if you know what you know somewhere
inside the model, RL can help you
extract that into your output policy. If
you don't know what you know at all,
right, at any level, RL cannot help you
there, right? like it can't help you uh
with the problem of like no having some
level of calibration.
>> Yeah. Sorry, just to follow up on that,
but if you're immun,
you get penalized in the function.
>> Um, in in SFP, well, you in some ways
implicitly you're getting penalized for
um anything that is not a reference like
assigning any probability mass to
something that is not this exact
sequence is penalized, right? So, in
some ways, SFT isn't doing the wrong
thing like this is a correct sequence.
The problem as SFT is the generalization
properties of this um that you know I
can't perfectly generalize off this one
example. You know there's two things two
sort of disentangle things that are
being taught here. One is sort of the
reference template and then the other
thing is uh the actual content of the
knowledge. Um and if I misgeneralize
based on the template I'm in big
trouble.
Great questions. Yeah.
Okay. Um the other thing that I want to
talk about is safety, right? Um once we
get to post-training, we have to really
start engaging with all the messy
realities of like how are people going
to use this? I think pre-training people
live in this like ivory tower of like
let's just compress the world. But
post-training people have to say like ah
yes but what if you know um people are
using our system for uh political
manipulation and disinformation and
post-training people might say ah yes we
see individualized spear fishing you
know we need to prevent this from
happening right like you you are the
last line of defense in some ways uh
between you and misuse of the systems
and so what do you do well you have to
apply safety controls to the system
right that will refuse to respond to
sort of malicious inputs like this is
kind of the de facto way by which these
companies enforce the safety controls
and so it falls upon the post training
key. Um unfortunately uh safety SFT
information seems even more sparse than
uh capabilities SFT information in
publicly available documents. Um I, you
know, pulled out the Llama 2 description
of how they do safety SFT. If anything,
this is one of the more detailed
descriptions. Um, but you'll see that
they don't even talk about how many
examples they used for safety tuning,
which is kind of crazy to me. Um, but
regardless, really the the framework by
which all the safety tuning approaches
operate is to balance two things. You
want to sort of balance like how often
am I allowing bad queries to get
through, which is I think the violation
right here. Um, and then you also want
to not overreuse because someone might
ask a question like, "How do I kill a
Python process?" And then if your bot's
like, "No, I can't let you kill
anything." that's very frustrating to
the user and so the false refusal rate
also needs to be low. So you want to
sort of control this and have a good
sort of paro trade-off um between the
two. Um and so what you do is you know
you basically create various kinds of
tailored data to navigate this
trade-off. Um in terms of the scale of
the amount of data you collect um you
usually have something like a few
thousand or tens of thousands of
examples. Um for example in llama 2 I
think it's about a few thousand examples
that are used for this process.
Um this state of affairs is a little bit
unsatisfying if I left you with only
that slide. So I will talk about a
little bit more detail. Um I think if
you want to look at um how post-
training is done maybe the only good
reference right now would be Tulu 3. Uh
this would be the post-raining pipeline
for um the OLO models that that Alan Ai
put out. Um and given the lack of
details about post- training in many
places, this is one of the few places
where you can see like a you know
reasonably performant post-training
pipeline in action. Um and they do have
for example a safety component which
consists of something like you know
50ish thousand examples uh total. Um and
if you look they all follow the same
fairly simple strategy for generating
SFT data which is kind of the following.
Um in a previous project they they had
this thing called wild chat where
basically they gave free API or free
chat access to a bunch of people so that
they can go out and use various kinds of
chat interactions. Um in exchange they
collected you know what they were doing
on those chats. Um and from that they
were able to basically you know filter
out a whole bunch of you know sort of
unsafe behaviors that were being
attempted to be done on these chat
interfaces as well as jailbreaks that
people attempted to do. And so they
mined these at scale and then created
essentially the preferred response which
is to you know resist the jailbreak in
one case and to say no in another case.
Right? Fairly very straightforward
approach. And I think from what we see
at least in the um sort of uh technical
reports and the model cards of of the
various closed source companies, similar
things are happening in that you look at
sort of the use your usage information,
you find unsafe behaviors, you get your
annotators to sort of play whack-a-ole
um with these bad behaviors. Okay, the
final thing I'll mention, and this is
related to what I said about, you know,
the number of examples that you need for
SFT. I think one thing if you haven't
played with SFP before that you will be
surprised by is if you have a
sufficiently capable model it does not
take very many examples to steer these
systems. So if you want to do something
like safety tuning, if you take 500
examples, let's say, you know, kind of
in the vein of, you know, you find a
bunch of unsafe stuff or you synthesize
a bunch of unsafe stuff and then you
write refusals and you put that into the
system, you'll find that even with as
little as 500 examples, um the rate at
which you follow malicious instructions
or other kinds of hate speech
instructions and so on drops
dramatically, right? And with 500
examples, you're you're really applying
this fairly surgical uh not surgical,
very small push to the model, but that
results in a fairly nice acrosstheboard
reduction in these safety issues um over
here. And so one way to think about it
is models already have a you know, am I
going to be a safe safe model or an
unsafe model access inside of it after
pre-training. So it does not take very
many examples to pull this out. Now, um,
one thing to to also remember at the the
end of this is just because you can
steer a model with very few examples
that doesn't mean that there's no
benefit to more examples. If you're open
AAI or anthropic and you want to enforce
really fine grain distinctions about
what is safe and not safe, you do need
very large scale data collection. Does
this doesn't really change that that
story. Okay. Um, so SFT at its best is
kind of this thing where if you're
extracting pre-training behaviors, like
it's already in there somewhere in
pre-training and all you want to do is
sort of pull out the right modes out of
the model, then instruction fine-tuning
um, works very very well with very
little data. As long as you have the
right high quality ones, um, you can get
the model to do what you want, right?
Um, and adding data or factually correct
ones can sometimes hurt you, at least in
terms of hallucination. And then
finally, you know, it doesn't take very
much data and so you can often focus on
quality instead of quantity. Good. Okay,
this is going to be the end of the data
part for SFTP. So if anyone has
questions, um, ask them before I move
on.
>> Oh yes.
>> How do we know what is like?
>> Yeah. Uh, the question was like how do
we know whether something's in
pre-training? Um, I think this is this
is the sloppiness of what I was saying,
which is that we don't really know per
se. Um, we can know what things aren't
in pre-training, right? Like we can look
for the kinds of generalization to like
for example programming languages that
are very rare. That's very hard using
SFT. So we we can show those things. We
can't show necessarily that like for
example safety is something that's in
pre-training per se.
Yes,
>> talked more about this and you talked
about RL, but there's this whole
question of like SF destroying features
or RLing them like
maybe
>> I'm not going to talk about that later.
The question was whether SFT is
destroying features and RL's like
pushing up or down. Um I think the lines
are very blurry between the two to be
honest. um especially when we get into
something like export iteration and all
these other things that look like SFT
with extra bells and whistles. So I
don't necessarily think it's a core
distinction between RL and SFT rather
that it's more of a distinction in the
uh kinds of feedback that we get right
SFT is this dense teacher supervision
whereas RL is sort of the self-taught uh
policy supervision and the other thing
about RL is that you know RL is that
you're you're uh getting your own output
from your own policy. So there's a sense
in which you don't maybe deviate quite
as far in what you're being reinforced
on. So and that's probably an important
part of what's happening. Okay. Um so
now let's talk about methods. You know,
for most of this class, we've been
excited to talk about methods. In this
part, it is about the most boring thing
because you just do gradient descent. I
just put the picture here as almost a
joke. You know, you just take loss
backwards and that's basically it. But
there is one nuance I do want to talk
about that is important. Um, which is
this increasing trend of turning uh
instruction tuning into part of
pre-training. Um, it used to be that
when when these things first appeared
that pre-training and post-training were
just these separate ideas um that you
would pre-train on web data and then you
would post-rain afterwards. But people
realized why separate two things when
you can mix them together. Um, and so
lots of highquality data a and even
instruction tuning data is now getting
mixed in at the tail end of training
when the decay phase usually of training
happens. Um and this really allows you
to scale up instruction tuning. It also
allows you to essentially emphasize
higher quality data. Um the impact of
this has been quite dramatic. Um and so
everyone as far as I know is doing it.
You can see it in most of the um sort of
model release reports that there's a
mid-training or like a second phase
pre-training with a different data mix.
Um, and importantly, uh, one thing that
I'll sort of, this is my pet peeve, uh,
I'll say is that now, you know, when
someone tells you something is a base
model, you know, that's kind of a lie
because a base model is usually about
like, oh, yes, predicting the next word
on internet data or something. Well,
really base models today are pre-trained
on like ultra chat and like who knows
what else. Those are like chat data sets
that are like synthetically designed to
make you good at chat. And so it's very
hard to say that this is like a base
model in the traditional sense of the
word. Um I've taken this example of a of
a two-phase training. I think this one's
from mini CPM. Um because I think they
show very nicely sort of the change in
the mix. So this first part is you know
the very standard oh whoops standard
pre-training phase where you've got all
sorts of internet data on the left um
and on the right you're kind of
switching to um this higher quality and
also very chatty data set. um you've got
like stack exchange QA, you've got uh
ultra chat, you've got um all sorts of
other SFT data and then you've decreased
the fraction of standard general purpose
pre-training data. Um so almost everyone
does this today. You can kind of think
of you know the point of this as saying
well the boundaries between pre-training
and instruction tuning and also
highquality data is just being blurred
very much. Um, yes.
>> Are the queries masked in this kind of
data? No, this is pure pre-training. And
so, you know, you're also uh predicting
the prompt as well. Um, but actually
that's not a huge difference because
some SFT recipes do also predict the
prompt.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So, the question was whether the
data quality is lower in the decay.
Usually the intuition is you want the
reverse that the decay is the most
important part of your training. It's
the part that's closest to deployment
during pre-training. Also, it's the part
with the lowest learning rate. Um, and
so for both of those reasons, maybe you
want to put the highest quality stuff
into the decay. Um, and so, you know, I
guess I guess book Chinese and and all
these things are supposed to be higher
quality. Certainly wiki and stack
exchange is usually considered high
quality.
>> Yes.
>> How is the mixture I guess for
retraining to be discussed on the
mixture side? do like cheaper models and
then from there you can use statistical
analysis to decide but then I guess for
like mid training and post training you
have to essentially run on the larger
model or do people still have like some
smaller model they use as a proxy I
assume there's like some reduction in
amount of information you could build I
guess you mention like what's there
about these data mixtures and where they
get the
>> yeah so um data mixtures I mean both for
pre-training and post- training are very
trial and error right um we do have
algorithms like many people have written
papers about things in this space. Um,
but I think they're fairly unreliable.
There's a lot of trial and error and
intuition that happens for this space.
Um, but the nice thing about this
two-phase training and this like sort of
mid-training stuff is that mid-training
is much shorter than full pre-training.
So if you're doing data mix optimization
for mid-training, you can run like
something like 10 of these for each one
of these on the left, right? Um, and so
this lets you not quite brute force the
problem, but it does let you try a lot
of ablations. Um, and so actually I
think the the usual way that I've heard
a lot of this done is actually in the
decay phase, you do a lot of data
ablations which are cheap to run and so
on and then you get estimates of data
quality and then you reflect that even
back to the first stage um into the
pre-training stage. Yeah. So to decide
the the pre-training mix often you
actually run a bunch of ablations on
decay and then you will figure out what
to put back or to how to set the uh
pre-training mix. The reason why you
don't just make pre-training high
quality is you just don't have enough
tokens, right? You'll run out of tokens
if you if you try to make Wikipedia your
whole pre-train.
>> Is there any intuition then based on
like you get from I guess how good the
downstream performance was the mixture.
Is there any intuition with how those
are like how how it's adjusted I guess?
That's very case by case of like how you
go from like downstream deltas on
ablations to mixes. There are systematic
ways like you can fit models and do
these things but they are often brittle.
Like what I've heard from from people is
that actually it's much more trial and
error than you think. Like you ablate a
domain, you make rankings over which
which ablations had the most impact um
and then you kind of decide what to put
in. Um actually a good example of this,
a fun example of this that's been leaked
is um when uh Meta got sued for using
books. Um in the court documents there's
actually a bunch of documents showing
you know some researchers doing
ablations and trying to estimate like
how useful are each of these like book
subsets. And so that's exactly the kinds
of things that happen and then
ultimately they'll decide based on that
what the mixes are.
Cool. Okay. Um so now we're done with
SFT. Um the algorithm part was very
short and now we get to talk about RLHF.
So this is the second phase. We're done
with sort of doing supervised
fine-tuning. Now we're going to do
something very different from
pre-training where we're just going to
upweight or downweight different model
outputs based on how a raider or in in
some cases a reward model decides how
good these responses are. And before we
get into like algorithms and stuff, I do
want to pause for one moment on this
slide and kind of talk about a
conceptual difference that I think is
actually quite important. Um maybe it's
less important for people that weren't
like originally coming from sort of
stats ML background and so on. But I
think there is actually a very different
sort of way of thinking about SFT or
even pre-training and RLHF, right? So in
pre-training, what are we doing? We're
doing generative modeling of some
sequence, right? So you have a
collection of sequences and you're
trying to predict the next word, right?
SFT is also the same. You've changed the
distribution, but you're predicting the
next word, right? Um so you can think
about this using your generative
modeling brain, right? This is purely a
generative modeling problem and then
you're just going to fit some
distribution. Now once we get to the
second part, the RHF, we are no longer
playing a fit a distribution game. We
are fitting a maximize a reward game,
right? Um so what we want is we want to
find some distribution. We still have a
distribution, right? This is a policy
now such that this policy is going to
maximize some downstream reward, right?
And maybe that reward is something like,
you know, how long your users are
engaged on your platform. Maybe that
reward is like what math problems you
can solve, but there's some sort of
reward. And I don't care if I've
mimicked some distribution, right? And
this is conceptually very different
because now in the second world, I can
totally collapse out my distribution
onto a single point for every input,
right? So for every prompt, my model
could have a single answer, right? Not a
distribution. and that would be okay as
long as they got a good reward, right?
Um, so that's a big important sort of
conceptual distinction to to sort of
keep in your mind. Um, and I wanted to
highlight it before we get into some of
the later bits.
Okay, so now why do we want to sort of
do this thing of doing reinforcement
learning? Um, we could just say why
don't you forever go and collect um, you
know, SFT data. Well, I think one thing
that is important for thinking about RL
is when we try to optimize what humans
want, there is sometimes a big
difference in what they say they want
and what they sort of generate. Um, and
that's one thing that we found in a past
study. I put this here because I find
this so funny even though it's a little
bit old now. Um, we asked a bunch of
freelance writers to uh summarize news
documents. Um and we found that a few
annotators actually preferred um
instructive Vinci which was the
predecessor to chatbt uh over their own
writing. Um and that was very strange
and we were like are these guys actually
doing annotations? So we interviewed
them and we we asked them like you know
why did you like the AI outputs over
your own writing and they they said well
you know I looked at it and I thought
actually this is pretty good stuff. And
so it turned out that, you know, they're
they're writers. They're good. They're
good at writing. Their summaries are
high quality. Like we check it for
quality, but actually when they looked
at it, they were like, "Huh, I didn't
realize that. That's actually a better
way of doing it." Right? So people
aren't really these like optimal
systems. And so, you know, when they
judge things, it's actually different.
And so because of this gap, sometimes
you might want to to rate outputs rather
than just to generate demonstrations.
Another reason is that um in some
domains, verification is a lot easier
than generation. uh math which I'll talk
about a uh more uh next lecture is a
prime example of this where you know
verifying a proof is probably much
easier than generating the proof and and
folks like deepseek have sort of gone
down that path for like
self-verification using models. Um
that's another place where this idea of
sort of having reinforcement learning
and judging yourself is a good idea.
So okay um I'm not going to cover what
people call RLVR today. That's its own
universe. um it's going to be an entire
lecture next time I'll talk about the
exciting you know promises of reasoning
models um but today I'm going to talk
about RLHF um and RLHF will have
different components and I'm going to
talk about you know data like how do we
collect it um and then I'm going to talk
about algorithms like how do we actually
do it and I'll talk about two major
families of algorithms um before sort of
talking about maybe some pitfalls at the
very end okay good so in RHF right the
highle way that we do things is now we
have a good model. After SFT, it follows
some instructions. We now put prompts
into the model. The model is going to
generate a couple different outputs. And
we usually do this by just sampling with
temperature one, right? At the end of
SFT, the model is pretty diverse. So,
this is a reasonable thing to do. A
raider comes in and rates all the
examples um and provides a ranking over
the examples um sometimes even a binary
ranking. And then a model is going to be
trained on those rankings. And we're
going to use standard reinforcement
learning techniques to maximize the
score that we get on that reward model.
And you know we go through the reward
model because um it might be easier to
train a verifier than to train a model
that does well directly. Okay. So how do
we get data for this thing? Um as I said
before the general way in which we do
this is to get pair wise ratings. And
so, you know, you're going to have an
interface like this where, you know, you
have a couple AI responses and you're
going to give a response saying response
one or two is better. Um, this is just a
standard annotation interface that I've,
you know, uh, gone and found, but most
places have similar things. We can now
look at what, you know, an actual
company would do in order to do this.
It's not that different, although they
have some nuances. Um, if you want to go
and like really read up on this, I would
suggest you look at the instruct GPT
appendix. It's kind of the last point at
which we have a glimpse into uh data
collection you know processes from
industry. Um and so at least in the
instruct GPT case they say okay we want
you to rate these outputs for being
helpful, truthful and harmless. So they
have to balance three things. Um
helpfulness is like how clear the
writing is or you know being sensitive
to internationality or not giving overly
long answers. You want to be truthful so
don't hallucinate. And then harmless,
you know, if it's unsafe, we want you to
say that you or we want you to, you
know, upweigh things that are sort of
refusing to respond to questionable
prompts. So, this sort of makes sense as
an omnibus objective for training chat
bots. Um, another very similar example
um that I found is uh this is I think
the only other example of a of a closed
source lab annotation uh being out in
the public. Um, this one is for Google
Bard. That was a quite a while ago, but
their annotations got leaked by some
annotators. Um, and you can see they
have a very similar structure of saying
like we want helpfulness. We want the
presentation of the response to be good.
And actually they're rating in a liyker
scale rather than pair-wise feedback.
Um, but they have a very similar
structure. It's not a very super long
set of instructions, but you get the
sense of like what kinds of things are
included like you know don't contain
inaccurate information or be coherent
and be sort of uh uh easy to consume. So
short uh for the user to read.
Um things have changed quite a bit since
then. Um there are a couple different
surveys of uh annotators. I think the
high level thing that I'll say before
going through the next two slides is in
general I think the worker distribution
for annotation has shifted upwards more
towards experts more towards higher cost
um and we kind of see that in
compensation and things like this. So um
if you look at the education level of
data annotators, this is for one of
scale AI's platforms. So it's not you
know representative of the full space of
data annotators for language models. Uh
but this is probably a reasonable subset
of those. Um the majority or a large
fraction of them uh are bachelor's
degrees or master's holders. So that's
like 70ome percent of these annotators.
Um and the age is like something like 35
uh is sort of the modal age. um and the
tasks that they're doing are often like
you know creative writing and technical
writing and so on um are often the the
task that these annotators end up
performing. Um this is you know one step
towards experts but I think even more uh
there's been a growth in the last year
or two in kind of bespoke annotators and
I think this is because a lot of the
labs are now pushing into deploying
these systems in like actual you know
white collar jobs and so you want
doctors you want lawyers you want these
people to annotate the responses you
want them to give SFT data um and so uh
there are these projects you know that
are internal to these uh companies like
open AAI where annotators are being
paid, you know, a pretty decent wage uh
per hour to do these annotations. And so
um if you look at sort of the median
wages, they're, you know, above $50 um
across a range of different topics. But
if you look at the experts, um some of
these experts are being paid, you know,
hundreds of or more than $100 per hour
to do annotation work. And so I think um
this is to say if your mental model of
an annotator was like you know lowcost
um uh pairwise feedback from somewhere
overseas that's not really the full
picture. Um there's a lot of annotation
happening now right now that's like very
bespoke very expensive um but it's kind
of also a pyramid. It's not like that
that lower cost scalable annotation has
gone away. Okay.
Um and to you know uh emphasize this
point to you getting this kind of data
is actually very challenging. That's why
the pay is high. That's why there's so
many data collection startups. Um I
think that the hard challenges now is
getting sort of verifiable annotators
especially ones where you know you're
sure that they're not using AI. Um if
you all have done like survey research
or crowd sourcing recently um I'm sure
you found that you know people are using
chat GPT as part of their survey
responses or as part of their annotation
workloads. Basically preventing people
from doing this is extremely extremely
difficult. Um it's also very difficult
to get truly correct responses when
people are under time pressure. Um, for
example, that Google Bard sort of
example, um, that was part of, I think,
some labor dispute where, um, the
annotators for Google Bard were saying,
"We have to check the correctness of
these long chat responses in under a
minute. It's impossible for us to do
that. You know, there's no way that we
can actually follow these instructions."
Um and to add right there's a growing
amount of sort of the expert uh data
collection but there's also a very large
amount still of sort of low paid um
annotation uh groups um scale I think
did quite a bit of this initially I
don't know if they still do um where
they outsourced a lot of this lowcost uh
annotation and got into quite a bit of
trouble and so in the same way that I
guess the the modern economy has like
this bifurcation um in terms of like you
know high and low wage jobs. We see the
same thing with annotations as well.
The final thing I want to talk about in
terms of um uh annotators is
demographics. Um one thing that's quite
important is the annotators have a
surprising amount of influence over what
the model does. Right? So post- training
kind of comes at the end and it's in
some sense the the final sort of shaping
step of the model before it gets shipped
out. So if you know you're not really
precise with how the annotators sort of
steer the model and your your annotation
groups have biases, you can actually end
up getting some like pretty surprising
behavior. So one of the studies that we
did um in the early days of instruction
cing um with one of my posttos between
Percy and I um uh was that uh we looked
at essentially which kinds of sort of
ideological opinions language models
were more aligned to. And we did this by
like asking sort of standard opinion
poll questions to language models and
seeing which human demographics they
were closest to. And so what you find or
what we found is that base models of
various kinds were kind of similar to
like Protestants or Roman Catholic
opinions um and kind of far from
Buddhist or Hindu ones. Um and then uh
what we found sorry is that if you
postrain these models so the the three
right columns you find that they're you
know more different from Protestants and
Roman Catholics um and becomes more
similar to Bu Bu Buddhists, Hindus and
atheists in terms of the kinds of
opinions that they give. And we were
like, "Huh, that's really strange. Why
these three groups?" Um, it turns out,
you know, if you look at the appendix of
the Instruct GPD paper, um, you find the
annotation annotators who were
annotating for these models and they
kind of line up, right? Like a lot of
Southeast Asians, um, and also people in
the West Coast of America. And that's
roughly the, you know, uh, demographic
groups corresponding to these. Um you
also find I guess uh another added note
is in the recent years there's been a
lot of findings that you know sort of
very subtle biases can transmit through
data. So one example of this is
something called emergent misalignment
right? If you have a piece of data um
trained from a model or generated from a
model that's been sort of trained to say
like I like owls or something and you
train on that like innocuous looking
data the model trained on it will
actually inherit a preference for owls.
And so there's all these like weird
kinds of like subliminal transfer
effects that can happen with data um
that are quite hard to catch. And so
that's one thing to be really really
quite careful about. Um and this is true
more generally. I think this whole you
know study of like LM political opinions
and so on can be like quite fragile and
sketchy at times. Um but uh the
annotator distribution and who your
annotators are also matters quite a bit
for the different kinds of error uh
different kinds of like more material
errors that your model might make. So
this is a study that's quite nice uh by
hosking at all um where they studied
like if I get really expert annotators
like people who like really care about
doing the job right versus you know sort
of random collection of crowd workers
how do their annotations differ? Um, and
they see show very nice striking results
that people who are just, you know,
non-expert annotators that are just kind
of paid on a platform really like to
emphasize formatting effects. Um, which
is kind of this row over here. You see
it's red. It's overenriched in sort of
these like non-expert annotators. On the
other hand, things like factuality or
inconsistency are things that are much
more over much more emphasized than the
expert annotators. Of course, it's much
much harder to test for factuality. And
so it's no surprise that, you know, if
you don't have experts, you don't
actually end up checking for these. This
is another way in which sort of your
your distribution of annotators ends up
mattering. Not demographic, but here um
how much they care and how what their
expertise is. Um it's been shown for a
while now that because of all these like
Oh, was there a question? Yeah,
>> I was asking how do you measure quality
in data? What are the
need to be higher quality than another.
>> Yeah. So, so the question was what does
it mean for one annotator to be higher
quality than another? Um I think there's
no gold standard rule where I you know
you can kind of mechanically turn the
crank and be like you are a good
annotator. I think I I'll maybe give two
different kinds of answers. One of them
is um a sufficiently detailed annotation
guideline should hopefully be like
semi-objective like you know you will
say like it should be factual and then
you'll define what factuality is and
then you might even have objective
criteria like in the first three pages
of the Google search you don't find
anything that contradicts it right and
if you can find something that you know
doesn't follow the guideline you can be
like ah yes you're not following the
rule that's one notion of a good
annotator the other notion of a good
annotator um is interanticator agreement
right um and that's a statement about a
population of annotators whether they
have high variance or not. I think the
only issue with that is it doesn't tell
you what the bias is. It tells you the
variance, right? And some tasks
inherently have variance. If you're
asking, do you like this? That's a task
with lots of variance. So annotator
agreement is not useful. If you're
asking is it factual, maybe it should be
lower, but you even if it's zero, you
don't know if you've asked the right
question, right? Or if they're all using
catchy BT, the variance will also be
zero, right? So it's very hard to assess
quality even though there's like ways of
maybe getting at that question. So is
the reason you're seeing like annotators
or like companies starting to recruit
more like experts or like highly
educated people who are to be annotators
because they give some like higher
quality or like more like well agreed on
answers or is it because like the data
that you're collecting is just something
that only these people can answer.
>> I think it's more of the latter. um you
know like maybe you need a lawyer to
check if a blue book annotation is
correct. You need to be relatively well
trained to be able to do that. Um you
know uh and there's also sort of tacet
knowledge of various kinds that maybe
you want to extract. So that's one of
the reasons it is true that I think in
general the platforms are moving more
towards like higher quality annotators
even for general annotation tasks. I
think a big part of this is because LM
have gotten good and if you don't like
inerson supervise people they will use
the cheapest you know LLM to generate
plausible looking answers um and so I
think you know there's a lot of
annotator shops whose value proposition
is basically like we have real people
that do real things and we will verify
that this is true for you right
>> cool okay yeah
>> what's the largest problem and I you
know you might be getting to this what's
the largest problem that like users a
domain specific model um as an as an
annotator.
>> Um so the question was what's the
problem with using domain specific
models as an annotator? I guess there's
two separate questions there. One is
like are domain specific models good and
then the other question is like should
we use models to annotate data? Um model
based data annotation is quite good.
It's, you know, if you're not at the
frontier and what you want to do is
basically catch up to the frontier,
model based annotation is very, very
good, right? Modern models are, you
know, probably much much better than uh
random crowdworker you can get. And so
model based annotations, good idea. Now,
domain specific models, well, can you
get domain specific models that are
better than, you know, the strongest
open models? Sometimes quite difficult.
And so, for that reason, I don't think
there's a unique advantage, for example,
to annotating with domain specific
models. In general, model based
annotations are a good idea.
Okay. So, you know, I didn't imp that
question, but we are moving towards uh
model based annotations. Now, um if you
look at LM generated annotations of
various kinds, you will find that you
know these models are surprisingly good.
Um when GPT4 came out, some of my
students and I did comparisons between,
you know, GPT4's annotations and
carefully curated human annotations. And
if you compare the rankings of systems,
they're pretty good. If you compare the
an agreement between humans to models,
the mode of humans to models, um they're
pretty good. Um and their cost is, you
know, order of magnitude less. So
that's, you know, all nice and good. And
at the time when we initially did this,
you know, back in the GPT4 era, it was
still not clear which way things were
going to go. like in the open world for
example were we going to move towards
you know expensive human annotation or
will everything just become in some ways
distillation from stronger models um I
think at this point it's been enough
years that we kind of know the answer
which is you know there's basically no
space for human collected data um if all
you want to do is to catch up to the
frontier capabilities um I think one of
the things that I found very interesting
at the time and sort of instructive
is um HuggingFace was trying to build an
open- source model called Zephier. Um
and one of the things that they really
wanted to do at the time was to not do
any model distillation. And so they
said, "Well, we're not going to use any
model based annotations or model based J
data. Um and we're going to spend a lot
of time and effort collecting human
data." So they went to the same, you
know, vendors that OpenAI and others do
to basically go and collect a bunch of
human data. Um but basically they found
that it was extremely time consuming,
costly and the results they were getting
were not actually better than using
modelbased annotations. And so in the
end, you know, they basically just used
model-based feedback for this, right? Um
which I think is instructive. They they
gave it a very real good shot, you know,
using the you know, resources that they
had, but in the end they ended up using
AI feedback. Um and this has basically
been the case like so you know for SFT
and also for um RHF we find that you
know ultra chat and ultra feedback which
are model generated are now uh very
standard. Tulu 3 which I I mentioned as
like one of the big almost flagship uh
open-source post-training uh processes
uh uses you know modelbased annotations
uh for all of its pipeline. And so this
is basically where we we've ended up um
in terms of you know should we use model
based annotations or not. Um models are
very good at following instructions very
scalable so you can collect the right
kinds of data that you want and this is
roughly where things are. Of course if
you want to push the frontier out you
don't get to necessarily play these
games except in limited circumstances.
Um and so you're still very much relying
on human-driven data collection.
>> Okay.
7B
is already very small.
>> Well, 7B is small now. I guess you know
at the time I guess 7B was kind of a
very respectable open source model. It's
like Llama is a 7B. Everyone loves Llama
7B. We too would like to train a 7B. And
so, you know, in that sense it was
respectable. Um I don't know if they
they went and tried it for their bigger
runs. Um but at least at that scale you
know they weren't seeing any
differences. Um I would be very
surprised if like they switched to the
bigger one and suddenly there was a big
difference. Uh cool. Okay. Um there are
other places where um you might do sort
of model generation that is not purely
distillation. Um anthropic had an early
work on selftraining. This was
constitutional AI where they kind of
prompted a model to generate safety
data. Um and then they trained you know
the model itself on that prompted data.
um and that allowed them to get sort of
a safer model uh out of the model and
that you can think of this as kind of a
very early um self post-training data
generation loop and the other paper
sorry the other project that I mentioned
to you of a self-instruct that's a
different kind of capability centric
version of this kind of idea. So you can
use models to kind of bootstrap your own
post- training data. But if you want
something like lawyers or scientists, um
you can't you know get world knowledge
without you know getting people to
annotate. So you're kind of stuck at
least for that with collecting human uh
annotators.
The other thing I'll mention is that
models are also very susceptible to the
same kinds of biases as humans.
Sometimes in ways that are uh quite uh
problematic as well like even more
problematic. Um there's been a couple
studies um you know after this kind of
wave of uh model generated data stuff
started coming out showing that actually
you know you could just push length of
your responses way out um and you would
continue to get improvements in the win
rates of sort of model judged uh
performance. Um and you know if you look
you know the one outlier here is uh
chatbt 3.5 basically saying like well
they're not just length hacking they're
actually a model that is actually
better. Um similarly um others showed uh
this was a very nice paper um showing
that you can just RLHF on length alone
and you could do quite well on many of
these benchmarks.
Okay, so that's roughly the data story,
right? You know, what kinds of who's
collecting the data, you know, what
kinds of things to be uh conscious of.
And then now in the remaining time that
I have, I'm going to talk about kind of
the algorithm. Um I'm only going to
briefly talk about PO because, you know,
both in the interest of time and because
I'm just going to do a more extended
treatment next lecture and then I'll
talk a little bit about DPO, which is
the cool fun bit. Okay, so now remember,
right, we're in the RHF regime. The goal
is the following. Uh I'm going to
maximize under my policy um the reward
that I get by sampling from that policy.
And this is like baby reinforcement
learning, right? Because people might
say we're playing bandits like this is
not true multi-turn interesting RL. And
that's roughly right. And so our
algorithms will also be quite simple.
So the objective that I just showed you,
maximize reward, it appears almost
exactly in the instruct GPD paper. If
you look at open open the paper up and
you go to equation two, you'll find
exactly the the kind of thing I wrote
down where you have, you know, you
sample from your RL policy. I want to
maximize my reward uh subject to this
second term which is really just a KL
divergence. It's all that it's saying is
I want to stay close to my pre-trained
model uh because I don't want to go too
far and become degenerate.
Um same thing is true um from Steenon at
all. This is another paper. Um you see
uh the reward in this case is a
pair-wise feedback model that you've
learned. So you train a binary
classifier on which of a pair of
examples is better and then you hill
climb on that reward. Right? So very
simple structure that we have. Now how
do we actually do that hill climbing? We
use an algorithm called PO. Um if you've
taken an RL class, you of course know
what PO is. Um if you haven't, I will
give you kind of a baby description of
what PO is. um also you'll have to
understand it for the the assignment. Um
so the very basic starting point is the
policy gradient identity right what I
want to do is I want to maximize my
rewards sampling from my policy how do I
optimize that well you know everything
in machine learning is gradient descent
so I take gradients right so I want the
gradient with respect to my parameters
and you can push the gradient in and do
the policy gradient trick and you can
show that that's equivalent to the
equation on the right so I'm just going
to you know take the gradient of my log
probabilities and weigh it by my rewards
and this really just looks like SFT key
but with weighted examples effectively.
Now you might say okay policy gradients
are great I love policy gradients but
the problem with policy gradients is I
need to sample every time I want to take
a optimization step and sampling is very
expensive right we've already talked
about in the systems parts inference is
often very complicated and hard whereas
training is very you know arithmetically
intense and good right and so I want to
roll out once and I want to reuse that
roll out multiple times so this is
something called off policy to do off
policy I want to sort of take multiple
steps but not go too far because if I go
too far my sort of estimates of my local
rewards kind of blow up. So this is
something called TRPO. The basic idea is
I want to take policy gradients but I
want to stay a little bit close to where
I am while you do something called an
importance waiting correction. Not going
to go into that in detail. Finally, PO
says, well, TRPO is a good idea, but
this sort of, you know, distance
constraint is actually kind of hard to
deal with. And so, I'm going to come up
with a heristic clipping thing that's
just going to discourage the RL
algorithm for going to places where I'm
too far from the original policy. Right?
Um, I'll go through the details of this
in the next lecture, so you don't need
to worry about it. But the main
progression of policy gradient off
policy, you end up at PO. Hopefully, you
roughly understand.
um PO already the equations look a
little bit gnarly right and so a lot of
people for many years have asked the
following question can we get rid of PO
and this was a big you know thing for
many people um and many reasonable
people thought about lots of good ways
of getting rid of PO and I I will tell
them to you so that you do not
necessarily repeat them in your own
research um for example you can say I
have a pair of examples and I can do SFT
but with a special kind of SFT if for
the pair that's good I will prepend a
good token. And for the example that's
bad, I'm going to prepend a bad token.
So you're going to append some tokens.
Um and then when I generate, I'm just
going to prefix my response with good.
So my model only generates good stuff.
So this is reducing PO to SFT or RL to
SFT. Does not work. Um people have tried
training the model only on the good
stuff. Um also does not work very well.
um you can train the reward model, get
LM outputs, select only the stuff that
the reward model selects and train on
that does not work as well, although it
does somewhat work. Um so many people
have tried many different iterations and
you know in the end we do now have a
thing that is much less complex than PO
works pretty well and is in many ways
looks just like SFT um and this is DPO
and so the algorithm is very very
simple. What we're going to do is we're
going to try to get rid of the
complicated parts of PO. What are we
going to get rid of? We're going to get
rid of the reward model. Um we're going
to get rid of anything that has to do
with on policy stuff. And by getting rid
of these two things, we're going to try
to make a much more simple uh RLHF
algorithm. Um and it relies on a very
simple intuition, right? Everything in
in deep learning is just taking gradient
steps in the direction of good things.
And so we're going to take steps in the
direction of the log loss of the good
stuff. And then we will take negative
gradient steps on the direction of the
bad stuff. In in other words, we're
going to reverse for uh the the log
probability of anything that is bad.
This is basically the most naive thing
you can do, right? Because you're doing
SFT on one hand and you're doing kind of
negative SFT on the bad thing. Um it
turns out that if you weight these two
appropriately, you will get an algorithm
that is actually pretty good. Um and
I'll give you the derivation because
it's all very simple. Um, so remember
our goal is to optimize this equation
over here, right? So this should look
familiar to you. The first term is my
expected reward under my policy pi
theta. The second term is saying that's
my KL distance. I want my uh policy to
remain close to my reference. That's
what I pre-train. Now I'm going to make
a assumption. This is the one strong
assumption that I'm going to make. And
I'm going to assume that pi my policy is
actually not a neural network at all. It
is the set of all possible policies. is
it is a nonparametric thing. It can
approximate anything, right? So if pi
can be anything, I can actually solve
that top problem closed form, right? I
actually know what the minimizer is. Um
and the minimizer is the following. The
the minimizer is actually to take my
original reference policy and to
exponentially tilt it by my reward. In
other words, every response gets upweed
or downweighted um with a weight x of
one over beta r, right? Based on how
good the reward is. This makes a lot of
sense. If the reward is really bad, I'm
going to exponentially downweight it. If
the reward's really good, I'm going to
exponentially upweight it, right? So
this is the closed form solution. If pi
can be anything, now we can then now
that we know this pi of r this perfect
solution, I can solve for the implied
reward. In other words, I can solve for
what is kind of the um r that would
induce this. And so I can solve for
that, right? I can put the pi r on the
left side and I can solve for the reward
that we would have.
And then we can take that implied reward
that I wrote down um and then I can
solve for what would happen in the
original RLH of objective. I plug in my
reward into that objective here into my
loss. Um and this gives the DPO
objective which is sort of very
intuitive. um it basically says take um
sort of gradient steps in the positive
direction um and then take negative
gradient steps in the bad direction,
right? And you can kind of already see
what's going to happen. This first term
over here, this is the good stuff. This
is the bad stuff on the right term here.
And they're going to be balancing each
other. Okay? And so if I take the
gradient of this, I think this is the
most intuitive form of DPO, at least to
me, um you have two things. for every
pair that you've had annotated, I'm
going to increase the likelihood of the
the example that won and I'm going to
decrease the likelihood of the example
that lost. Um, and I'm going to scale
sort of the step size in some sense by
um how much my implied reward model is
wrong. Like did my model already assign
a very high reward to the winning one?
If it did so, I will take a small step.
But if I was very wrong and I said, "Oh,
these two are almost equal." I had same
probability but in that case I will
actually take a much bigger step size.
Right? So based on the probability
differences I will take bigger or
smaller step sizes on this sort of
differential log prop objective. So
hopefully the the um action of this
gradient objective is quite clear uh to
people.
Okay. So this is actually much much
simpler than PO, right? Because all I'm
doing is taking gradients and we all
know how to do that with our standard uh
processes. Um, and I think the nice
thing is that it does work reasonably
well. I think for for a while, um,
people were very obsessed with like is
DPO better than PO or vice versa. I
think the answer now is maybe it doesn't
matter very much unless you're like at
the frontier training the very best
model. Um, DPO is is reasonably good and
it's good enough for for Llama, it's
good enough for me. Um if you go and
open up the llama tech report you'll
find um you know that they basically had
this like nice outer loop training where
you know they had their model they sfted
it they did DPO and then they used that
DPO model to then sort of generate
candidates that they rejection sample
then they repeated this process so
there's the outer loop on top of it but
basically the core RLHF primitive for
llama was DPO
um in the years since uh there's been a
lot of different variants um of DPO
there was simpio which basically changes
sort of the waiting. So instead of using
pyreff um you have this like y of l
normalizer um there was length
normalized dpo which normalizes by the
length um in order to avoid certain like
length hacking issues that seem to
arise. Um but really um none of these
variants maybe seem to matter very much.
Um, one of the things that I'll mention
that I thought was very interesting was
these results are very very contingent
on the specifics of the experiment
setup. So, even at AI2, you know, uh,
there was a paper that was like, well,
it turns out that if you go from DPO to
PO, um, you'll get a better result. Um,
but then, you know, they also had a
paper for for uh, Tulu 2 where they said
actually if you do DPO, right, um, you
can do better than PO. Um, and so
depending on how you execute this, um,
one can be better than the other. I'm
sure you have experiences reading deep
learning papers and so on where like the
results are very fragile, right? Um, so
maybe the takeaway from all of this is
that these DPO variants are actually,
you know, close enough to the right
thing to give you pretty good
performance in many cases, right? This
core idea of take gradient step in the
right direction and take negative
gradient step from the bad stuff works
reasonably well as long as you set the
step sizes right. Okay, I will end with
the last few slides on things to watch
out for in RLHF. So, one of the things
to watch out for is overoptimization.
And this is maybe one of the biggest
things um to give you also historical
context, right? When uh instruct GPT
came out and like you know people were
very excited about this. I think there
was a very real question of like can we
RHF our way to like you know super
intelligent systems or whatever maybe we
can just collect enough thumbs up thumbs
down. um turns out that is actually
quite challenging um because you you
find that if you try to like really push
the RLHF process forward um you'll start
overfitting to your learned reward
model. Right? So the kale regularizer
that I talked about is really critical
in a lot of cases um in order to prevent
your sort of um optimization process
from overfitting um your reward model at
least if your if your uh optimization
process is very good. The other thing
that I'll talk about um is uh model
collapse. Um so people have seen lots of
times where RL models have much less
diversity. They're like concentrated on
a few different possible outputs. Um and
this connects back to what I said
before, right? RLHF models um are really
no longer modeling a distribution which
comes with its own inherent diversity.
It's a policy that can collapse as long
as it gets a good reward, right? So this
is another thing that that uh sort of
RHF models have really struggled with um
in recent years. Um so actually I'm
going to I'm going to skip this because
it's we're at time. Um and I think this
this entropy and mode collapse thing
actually ends up being quite important
uh even today. Um and the GPT4 era
actually was one of the few plots that
OpenAI put out where they said actually
we have a few open problems left and one
of the open problems they had was
actually our models are unccalibrated
after we do RHF. which you can see in
this plot over here. Um I don't think
anyone has really solved that yet. Um
the uh anthropic folks also had a
argument saying like well it's naturally
unccalibrated. You could recalibrate
sometimes but not always. This becomes
very important in the next lecture when
we talk about things like RLVR where the
the entropy and exploration is actually
quite critical for the model to explore
all the possible solutions and to make
progress on some of these very hard
problems.
Great. Um so to you know put it all
together right um RHF data collection is
also very hard. I think part of the
thing about post training is it's very
complicated messy process because a lot
of it is getting good data and getting
good data is always very difficult. Um
RLHF algorithms are are quite complex.
PO is especially difficult. I'll I'll
talk a little bit about it um next
lecture. Thankfully we do also have a
simpler variant there called GRPO that
works pretty well. That's what you'll do
in your assignments. Um but this is one
place where there's been a lot of recent
developments. Um finally I think in
terms of RHF the you know one of the big
big problems is overoptimization and the
transition to the next lecture is going
to be you know is there rewards where we
won't overoptimize right where we can
just kind of dump in compute and the
model performance just keeps
monotonically getting better and that's
one of the reasons why uh what people
call RLVR is just so you know been so
impactful. Thanks. See you all Thursday.